<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen at White-Hall, January XIV. 1693/4 by Geo. Hooper.</title>
            <author>Hooper, George, 1640-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26068</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09340305</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09340305</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1310:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen at White-Hall, January XIV. 1693/4 by Geo. Hooper.</title>
                  <author>Hooper, George, 1640-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Warren for Walter Kettilby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Publish'd by Their Majesties command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John VII, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:42782:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>HOOPER</hi>'s SERMON BEFORE THE King &amp; Queen, At <hi>Whitehall, Jan.</hi> xiv. 1693/4.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42782:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42782:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the King &amp; Queen, AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>January</hi> xiv. 1693/4.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEO. HOOPER,</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd by Their Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Warren,</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhop's Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:42782:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42782:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the King and Queen.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN vii. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If any one will do His will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whether it be of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>UPon our Bleſſed Saviour's Appearance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, there muſt have been much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry and Diſpute concerning Him. His Miracles and his Doctrines were both of them ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and extraordinary; they amazed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the World: his mighty Works making a change in the courſe of Nature, and his ſurpriſing <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> tending to as great an alteration in the <hi>Doctrines</hi> they had received from their <hi>Fathers</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42782:4"/>
               <hi>Rabbies.</hi> Neither of them could be oppos'd; his <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> not to be deny'd, and his <hi>Words</hi> not to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted: and yet the People knew not well what to think; were not come to a Reſolution, whether he was to be believ'd; whether he ſpake from God, or Himſelf, or it may be from an evil Spirit.</p>
            <p>The People were <hi>aſtoniſhed at his Doctrine,</hi> he <hi>ſpake it with</hi> that ſupernatural <hi>Authority. Never man ſpake like this Man,</hi> was the Return, the Officers ſent to apprehend him, make, in this Chapter, to their Maſters the High-Prieſt and Phariſees. Neither did any man ever do like him: for <hi>when Chriſt ſhall come, will he do more miracles than this man?</hi> was the Challenge of thoſe that did believe. And that the reſt <hi>believed not on him, who had done among them ſuch works as no man had done,</hi> was judg'd by our Lord, in this Goſpel, to be the great <hi>Aggravation</hi> of their Sin. For his Works were evident unexceptionable Teſtimonies of his Miſſion, and to them he frequently remits the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers</hi> for their full Conviction.</p>
            <p>And yet, for all this, there were not many who believed on him; thoſe not the Rulers or the Learned: neither continued they long in that juſt and well-grounded Perſwaſion. Thoſe who had ſeen his late great Miracle of the Loaves; had fed of it, had ſatisfied their <hi>Hunger</hi> and their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42782:4"/>
               <hi>Doubts,</hi> almoſt all left him, in a very little while, for one <hi>hard Saying. Many of his Diſciples went back, and walked not with him,</hi> inſomuch that the <hi>Twelve</hi> were asked, Whether they would depart from him alſo? And when afterwards he came up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there was <hi>great murmuring concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him. Some ſay, he is a good man; ſome ſay, nay, but he deceiveth the people.</hi> They knew not how he ſhould know Letters, who had never learn'd; and therefore in the beſt conſtruction they would make, Was not his Doctrine from himſelf, and of his own Deviſing? Now from the Reflection of theſe Surmiſes, he here juſtifies himſelf in ſuch a manner, as retorts all the blame of thoſe <hi>Doubts</hi> upon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers</hi> themſelves: giving them a plain account of this their Ignorance, which thus perplexes them. <hi>My Doctrine,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is not my own, but from him that ſent me:</hi> and ſo much you could not but have known, had you been rightly qualified for it. But that after which you ſeem to be ſo curious and inquiſitive, you are not very likely to underſtand, in the Method you take, and the Diſpoſition you are of; if ye would diſcern the Will of God, ye muſt be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do it: <hi>He that will,</hi> is deſirous and ready to, <hi>do God's Will, he ſhall know it.</hi> This is the <hi>Truth</hi> directly and primarily intended by the <hi>Text,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42782:5"/>to the Doctrine as propounded to be known. There is too another Conſequent to this, and to which the Words may extend; regarding the ſame Doctrine as known already: <hi>If any one will</hi> or ſhall <hi>do the will of God,</hi> which he now knows in part, <hi>he ſhall know</hi> it better and further; be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and advanced in that his Knowledge, by the Practice.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> Propoſition is this; <hi>If any one is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do the Will of God, as ſoon as he may have the Favour to be acquainted with it; he, when it ſhall be told him, ſhall not fail to know, and diſcern it.</hi> And this <hi>Willingneſs</hi> to <hi>do,</hi> we are to underſtand to be ſuch, as may anſwer in ſome meaſure to the Dignity, Reaſonableneſs, and Neceſſity of the Work; the <hi>Doing</hi> the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>great God:</hi> a <hi>Will</hi> the moſt <hi>wiſe,</hi> the moſt <hi>holy,</hi> the moſt <hi>juſt,</hi> moſt worthy to take place; to which it is our <hi>Honour,</hi> our <hi>Perfection</hi> and our <hi>Happineſs</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and no leſs our <hi>Duty</hi> and our <hi>Interest:</hi> we that have been created by the <hi>Power</hi> of his <hi>Almighty Will,</hi> ever ſince ſuſtained by its graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Providence,</hi> ſtill dependant, and eternally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the <hi>Favour</hi> or <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> of his <hi>final Will</hi> to be hereafter declar'd, when he ſhall come to call us to account for that part of his Will he has already injoyn'd.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:42782:5"/>
            <p>The <hi>Will</hi> of this our <hi>great LORD,</hi> he that is thus willing <hi>to do,</hi> will firſt be as earneſt and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>to know;</hi> diligent and heedful in his Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; punctual and exact in his Inquiries; leſt he ſhould be defective or miſtaken, when he comes to act, in an Affair of ſo high a Nature, and of ſuch weighty Conſequence.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a deſire <hi>to know,</hi> it muſt be confeſs'd, would certainly follow: But this may not ſeem at firſt ſight to have been meant here by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; and though he reflects upon his Auditors Unwillingneſs <hi>to do,</hi> yet their Eagerneſs <hi>to know</hi> muſt we not ſuppoſe him to admit? For very great Multitudes follow'd into Deſerts to hear him: and much Diſcourſe, and great Debates there were, concerning him and his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all this Appearance of Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to hear and to be inform'd, there might have been no ſuch great deſire to know.</p>
            <p>For Curioſity and Inquiſitiveneſs is ſatisfied of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with ſomething ſhort of Knowledge. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſometimes to have went to the Place, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther others throng; to have made up one of the Aſſembly, and to have ſeen the fam'd Preacher. Men too when they hear, do not always attend; their Eyes gaze, and their Thoughts wander: Or if they do, it may be to the graceful Meen, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42782:6"/>ſweet Voice, the elegant Style, the pathetick or the rational way of the Diſcourſe, and not to the merit of the Argument, and purpoſe of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>they went not out into the wilderneſs to ſee a Reed ſhaken with the wind,</hi> yet they might go to ſee a Man that cur'd ſuch a Neighbour; to be preſent at ſome ſtrange ſight themſelves; to be able to report a Miracle of their own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; or to be Gueſts at one of thoſe wonderful Entertainments. Or elſe they might have went to hear one, who ſpar'd not the Greateſt, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buk'd the High-Prieſts, and corrected the Scribes and Phariſees.</p>
            <p>They might too have heard ſo much, as not to be ignorant, and yet not ſo much as to know; as much as would let them underſtand ſomething of the Diſpute in faſhion, and enable them to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain one ſide of the Argument; to hold up Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and to talk of <hi>Jeſus:</hi> but not to make a judgment in good earneſt; a practical one, by which they would determine their Actions, and which they would ſtand by with their Lives: ſuch a real effectual one, as they would have made, had they been willing to do.</p>
            <p>But though in the general, they might be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to <hi>know,</hi> and not only <hi>hear him gladly,</hi> but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42782:6"/>
               <hi>do many things for his ſake;</hi> yet many things ſtill there might be, which they might be either unfit or unwilling to underſtand: either their former Prejudices might obſtruct, or their Intereſts and Paſſions diſturb and oppoſe; if their will <hi>to do God's Will</hi> were not firm and reſolute, ſtrong enough to ſet aſide thoſe Hinderances, and over-rule all Contradictions.</p>
            <p>The power of ſingle Praepoſſeſſion, and ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Prejudice, is well known. An Opinion once poſſeſs'd of us claims a kind of Right, a legal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be ſhewn it; and if the Poſſeſſion be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and time out of mind, the Title is not eaſie to be evicted: But as a Prejudice, it is a Point al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready judg'd and ſettled, hardly to be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to queſtion before the ſame Judge, much leſs to be revers'd by him. And for ſuch Reaſons only, it might have been hard for an innocent Phariſee, to find the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Obſervations</hi> of his <hi>Sect</hi> diſparag'd and diſcharg'd; thoſe which the <hi>great Rabbies</hi> had encouraged, and the Tradition of their Fore-fathers had recommended: but much leſs could he ever admit, that the <hi>Ceremonial Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> was to give way, and that a Greater than <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf was now ſpeaking unto them. He might be willing <hi>to do the Divine Will,</hi> as he now apprehended it to be, conformable to his <hi>Education</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:42782:7"/>and <hi>Practice:</hi> willing <hi>to do the Will of God,</hi> but as willing, at the ſame time, to do the will of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if now we ſuppoſe this Phariſee to be ſome <hi>governing Maſter,</hi> whoſe Authority is founded in his Knowledge of thoſe Traditions; and whoſe high ſatisfaction it is to fit in <hi>Moſes</hi> his Seat, and to be called <hi>Rabbi:</hi> he is then ſo much addicted to them, not only by Praepoſſeſſion of Mind, but by the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingagement of his <hi>Affections,</hi> that ſhould <hi>Moſes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf have come, he might not have been willing to leave the Chair; much leſs to hear any of his old oracular Learning upon the Law, which made him Great, but that of no effect, cenſur'd and condemn'd by this <hi>Law-giver.</hi> For he is not ſo willing <hi>to do God's Will,</hi> as to preſerve his own Place and Reputation; that we may not imagine he would be controll'd by our Saviour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to learn from the <hi>Galilean,</hi> and one that never knew Letters.</p>
            <p>But ſtill if we go further, and underſtand ſome one of the avaritious, malicious, lewd and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Phariſees; as unwilling then as he would be to forego his Vices, ſo unwilling will he be to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Law againſt them; much more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a New one, which ſhall oppoſe him with a more expreſs, and more peremptory Declaration.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42782:7"/>And on this account it was, that all our Saviour's <hi>Miracles</hi> were not of force enough to convince them of his Authority: His ſingle <hi>Sermon on the Mount,</hi> and the <hi>Holineſs</hi> there preſcrib'd, would never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to be perſwaded by him. The Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees that were covetous, derided him for his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Directions: and thoſe who brought the Adultereſs before him, and were not guiltleſs enough from the ſame Crime to proſecute it far, as they left the Accuſation, ſo they fled from his Reproof. They all therefore ſought inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtructed by his Words to have ſomething thence to inform againſt him. As many Vices as there were, ſo many Adverſaries there generally were to his Doctrine; practical Prejudices, with which they were praepoſſeſs'd, as with ſo many <hi>Daemons;</hi> and which would not be perſwaded, nor argued out: for what had they to do with the Son of <hi>David?</hi> This is that Diabolical Race, which paid him leſs reſpect than the Devils themſelves; They would not come out at his Command: but rather treated Him, as thoſe impure Spirits did the Sons of <hi>Sceva, fell upon him, and drove him out;</hi> not remov'd him out of a Country by Intreaty, as the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> but out of the World, with all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight and Cruelty; as the greateſt Malefactor of the <hi>Three;</hi> as guilty of <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42782:8"/>
               <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> becauſe guilty of <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to their <hi>Corruptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For he that has no mind to be deny'd any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Pleaſure he indulges, or any ungodly Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage he values, will be very averſe from hearing, that ſuch an Abſtinence is the <hi>Will of God;</hi> will either cavil at the Meſſage, and diſpute its Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or wreſt and interpret it to his own Will. Nay ſo far, we know, Men otherwiſe of <hi>good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings,</hi> may be brought by <hi>Adherence</hi> to their <hi>Luſts,</hi> as to deny the natural Notions of common Juſtice, and to queſtion the being of their Maker: they will not comply with the Directions he has given; and therefore they will neither know his Pleaſure, nor his Perſon: <hi>who is the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>great Impediment of Knowledge</hi> our Saviour here means; a <hi>Dullneſs</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> not for want of <hi>Ability,</hi> but <hi>Will</hi> to apprehend; in thoſe <hi>who hear, and will not underſtand; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſee, but will not perceive; becauſe their Heart is waxed groſs, and their Ears are dull of hearing, and their Eyes have they clos'd; lest they ſhould ſee with their Eyes, and hear with their Ears, and underſtand with their Hearts, and be converted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas on the other ſide, if there were a <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to do God's Will,</hi> there would be no need of any great <hi>Intellectual Abilities</hi> to perceive it.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42782:8"/>The Duties of Juſtice and Mercy are eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd by the meaneſt Capacity; Judgment to come, Man naturally forebodes; and the Being of a God, it is a Difficulty to the Underſtanding not to allow: The Doubts and Obſcurities ariſe not from the Nature of the things to be conſider'd, nor from the Weakneſs of the Faculty that ſhould conſider, but from the Prevarication of our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Deſires; we are ſway'd by ſome indirect means, that appear not to have any Influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; ſome little favourite conſideration, which we are loth to own; but by which we are govern'd effectually.</p>
            <p>Had the Auditors therefore of Chriſt come rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſpos'd to have obey'd God's Will, without any Reſerve for their own; with no Inclination nor Paſſion but for his Service; they would have perceiv'd the Almighty Power in the Miracles our Saviour did, and diſcern'd the Divine Law in the Inſtructions he gave them: had they firſt ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped themſelves of their Prejudices, and their Luſts; they would quickly have forſaken all the reſt of the World, and followed him. If the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of <hi>Moſes</hi> had prevailed upon them <hi>to do God's Will</hi> with their whole Heart, and whole Soul, the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> would have own'd their <hi>Meſſiah:</hi> and had they been true Diſciples
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42782:9"/>of the Law, and followed that their <hi>School-maſter;</hi> it would have <hi>led them to Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Aſſertion primarily intended by the Text, regarding thoſe who were then to receive the Goſpel: there remains the other, reſpecting us who have already received it; <hi>If any one will do the Will of God, which he does know, he ſhall know it better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what was but intimated before, is here more expreſly to be obſerved; that <hi>Knowledge</hi> is of two kinds, the one <hi>ſimple,</hi> and <hi>ſpeculative;</hi> where the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> conceives and aſſents by it ſelf, our Will and Affections ſtanding by, and taking no part: the other <hi>mixt,</hi> and <hi>compounded</hi> by the intervention of the Will, where that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in what is to be aſſerted, or practiſed, and muſt concurr in the Allowance of it.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, even the <hi>ſpeculative,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it conſiſts in apprehending what the <hi>Doctrine</hi> means, or in conceiving its Truth and Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is by Practice both ways very much facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated and confirmed. In <hi>Mathematical Sciences,</hi> the way of performing a <hi>Problem,</hi> however demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratively aſſigned, remains further to be verified by the <hi>Operation;</hi> and in conſiderations of Nature, the Will of God wrought by his own hands, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42782:9"/>beſt method of <hi>Knowledge</hi> is that which is <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,</hi> and Works too; which puts the <hi>Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials</hi> into our hands, and looks not only upon their Surface in ſome ſingle View, but turns them, and ſurveys them on all ſides; weighs and examines, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens and ſearches their inmoſt Receſſes. For this ſort of Truth, as Gold, is to be labour'd after, and dug for; and not to be judg'd only by the Sight, but by the Touch and the Scale, or by the Hammer and the Fire. And if this be true in the <hi>Speculation</hi> of what God himſelf has been pleaſed to make, much more will it be in the Knowledge of that, which we, by his Command, are to Doe. For it can be no otherwiſe with the practical Doctrine of God, than it is acknowledged to be in the Arts and practical Profeſſions of Men: where the true Inſight is not ſo much from the Apprehenſions we may have by Diſcourſe and Meditation, as by Dealing in them, and being actually exercis'd and converſant about them: the knowledge of ſuch things as are to be done, which ariſes from our mental Conceptions, being but as the rough <hi>Draught</hi> or firſt <hi>Lines</hi> of a <hi>Picture;</hi> and that when it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated by experience, as a finiſh'd Piece, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with all its Lineaments and Colours. Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Notional Knowledge is as the Picture, and the Active as the Thing it ſelf: the one being but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42782:10"/>in Imagination, and as a Dream; and the other Real, and Solid, and Senſible. For whoever is our Inſtructor, and how plainly ſoever he may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs himſelf; we are yet to learn in things pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical, from <hi>Exerciſe</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> the laſt Maſter and the beſt Interpreter.</p>
            <p>This obtains in the Arts of Government, or War, or Merchandiſe, in any of the Affairs of this World: and holds as true in Ethical Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the Buſineſs of Religion. For as the Natural Philoſopher forbad the uninſtructed in <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry</hi> to enter his School; ſo the Moraliſt has, it is known, diſcouraged his too Youthful Auditors as unfit for his Lectures: not only becauſe they might not yet patiently hear of Moderation of their Paſſions and Pleaſure; but becauſe, till they had begun to practiſe it, they could not rightly underſtand it, <hi>not</hi> being yet, <hi>by reaſon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd to diſcern ſuch Good and Evil.</hi> Temperance, for example, is in this, like to the Pleaſures, from which it orders us to abſtain, that it cannot be conceived only from Words, muſt be taſted too, if we would know its Nature and its Reliſh. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice likewiſe and Charity are beſt underſtood by their Practitioners: thoſe in any caſe of Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would prove better Directors than the more ſtudied Caſuiſt; would ſolve and remove the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42782:10"/>Doubts, which theſe would ſerve only to intricate and to multiply. They would too by the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of thoſe Vertues, ſee more reaſon for them; more of their Suitableneſs to the well-diſpoſed Nature of Man, than Books could ſpeak, or The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory diſcover. In like manner; He that conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and devoutly prays to his <hi>Maker,</hi> beſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the Nature of the Duty, and beſt perceives the Uſe and Comfort of it: better than thoſe who have heard, or made long Diſcourſes about it. The Meaning of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Prayer,</hi> is more ſenſibly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by one that prays it over to God, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and concernedly, with Dependance on the <hi>Divine Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> in reference to the <hi>daily Occurrences</hi> of his Life; than it can be by the critical Conſideration of the beſt Commentator alone. And he that thus daily addreſſes to his <hi>Father which is in Heaven,</hi> with a <hi>dutiful Reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>filial Truſt,</hi> has more of ſatisfactory Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and inward Peace, than the <hi>Children of this World</hi> can imagine, or he himſelf expreſs.</p>
            <p>And thus, taking the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> by it ſelf, and unaffected with our <hi>Will,</hi> the <hi>Will of God</hi> is better <hi>known</hi> by being <hi>done.</hi> If done by others, it is more conſpicuous to us on their Lives, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter explain'd and illuſtrated by the Example; but if by our ſelves, and made one of our own Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42782:11"/>it is then taken into us, habituated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated in us, intimately and intirely percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Whereas too all Humane Deſigns are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fairer in the Idea, than the Practice; on the contrary, the <hi>Divine Pleaſure</hi> muſt be more lik'd and approv'd, when it is reduced into Act, and really exhibited, who ever ſhall put it in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but much more will it delight us, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by our ſelves; it will then become our Pleaſure too, and we look back with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of our Creator, and <hi>ſee that All is good,</hi> which <hi>we have done,</hi> according to his Will.</p>
            <p>But <hi>ſecondly,</hi> if we conſider this Knowledge, not formed by the Underſtanding only, but with the agreement of the Will; as it is in all the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this and the other World: then Doing and Practice will be found ſtill more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the advancing and completing it. For though in Matters of Knowledge the Will has no direct proper Concurrence, nor is the Conſent of it ſtrictly neceſſary to the Aſſent of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; yet it has ſuch a tacit but effectual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, ſuch a domeſtick conjugal Authority, that the Underſtanding is ſeldom firmly or long on that ſide, to which the other Faculty is not incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and therefore as far as doing contributes to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42782:11"/>reconcile, keep up, and fortifie the Will; ſo much it prepares and diſpoſes for the preſerving, as well as the receiving, of Knowledge.</p>
            <p>Now the doing of <hi>God's Will,</hi> does operate on <hi>ours,</hi> with this threefold Advantage.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Duty</hi> takes off from the ſtrangeneſs of it, and removes all the imaginary Difficulty we fanſied to be in the Work, before we ſet upon it. The Task was before repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, as ſome good Man may be to thoſe who have not practiſed him; a rigid, moroſe, auſtere thing: whereas, after Converſation, and ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, there is nothing whoſe Company leſs offends, or which we better affect. While we keep off at a diſtance from the Exerciſes of Religion; its Enemies, and ours, have a fair Opportunity to miſ-repreſent, and to raiſe up ſuch Imaginations in us as ſhall agree with their Intereſt: but if we would but approach, and make tryal, we ſhould diſcover the Calumny; it would then appear, that there was <hi>no Lyon in the way,</hi> or at the end; and that the falſe Spies we had ſent forth to diſcover the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> had made to us a moſt unfaithful Deſcription. And may I not ſay, that is with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> it ſelf, as with thoſe few <hi>edifying Orders</hi> in Uſe with us about it? It is a burdenſome Yoak, an intolerable Impoſition, unneceſſary, fooliſh,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42782:12"/>any thing that Detraction ſhall think fit to ſay, to thoſe who are ignorant of it, and not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it: whereas if we came a little nearer, and experienc'd it our ſelves, we ſhould then begin to wonder at the unjuſt Surmiſes we were brought to entertain before; and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be more unreaſonable, and more vain, than ſuch Repreſentations as thoſe.</p>
            <p>For to give the Caſe of all Chriſtian Duties in the Inſtance of one, the <hi>Holy Communion;</hi> how many are they who are well enough inform'd, that it is a neceſſary part of <hi>Divine Worſhip;</hi> a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> to which we are as much obliged, as we were to the other? And yet how are Men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally kept off from it by ſtrange Conceits, ſuch as can have no place, but in idle Minds? It is a Myſtery, from which the <hi>profane</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> ſhould abſent: but to many, who are to be incouraged to come, it is the more a Myſtery, becauſe they come not at all. There is ſomething in it, they know not what, they are afraid of: and the Action, inſtead of being Reverend, is Frightful to them. Upon the thought of it there is a Damp and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy on their Minds; though the Subject of it be Thanks and Praiſe, and the Invitation be to a Feaſt. Though there be no more ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Sins, than what they ſhould make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42782:12"/>every day; no other Renunciation of them, than what their <hi>Baptiſm</hi> preſumes already; yet they imagine ſome new terrible Work is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and that they ſhall come under danger of Condemnation, if they go thither; from which too they ſhall eſcape, if they ſtay away.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>firſt Apprehenſions</hi> of a <hi>God,</hi> no wonder if ſome natural fearfulneſs ſeizes us; and when the ſpiritual World is mentioned, Spectres may ariſe in weaker Minds, and ſeem to ſtand in their way: but if they will but go on, theſe empty Shadows will immediately diſappear; and if we draw near to the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> we ſhall not be amaz'd and diſ-heartened, but aſſured and encouraged by that Gracious Preſence.</p>
            <p>Many vain Fears there are in the Chriſtian War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, before which often the Raw and Unexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd ſhamefully fly without a ſtroke ſtruck, to be cured, as we ſee, by Uſe and Action: and ſome groundleſs Averſion there may be to our Duty, which the Practice of it will reconcile: but there is beſides much real Danger, and direct actual Oppoſition, to be conſidered in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For to confeſs the <hi>Truth;</hi> we are not only as <hi>Strangers to the Will of God,</hi> but there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within us, which is an <hi>Enemy to it, and wars
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42782:13"/>against it:</hi> Rebellious Luſts, that would be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make a Reſiſtance; and watch all Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, to withdraw the Obedience of the Will, and to corrupt the Integrity of the Judgment.</p>
            <p>The Evidence of the <hi>Truth</hi> may have brought us to ſome Knowledge, and our <hi>Carnal Affections</hi> were forc'd at preſent to ſuffer the <hi>Conviction</hi> of the <hi>Mind:</hi> And had the well-inform'd Soul been <hi>active</hi> and <hi>diligent,</hi> ſetting the <hi>Will</hi> on work, and employing it upon its <hi>acknowledged Duty,</hi> ſubduing and ſuppreſſing the <hi>contrary Inclinations;</hi> it might then have gained an <hi>intire Conſent,</hi> and eſtabliſhed for ever its <hi>just Dominion.</hi> But if, on the other ſide, it be idle, and ſees not to the Execution of its <hi>own</hi> and the <hi>Divine Pleaſure;</hi> this is both a ſure Indication, that our ſenſual part remains too pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful; and a ſad Prognoſtick, that it will quickly recover its ground, and, finally prevail. When the <hi>Convictions</hi> begin to <hi>cool,</hi> and the <hi>Impreſſions</hi> on our <hi>Mind</hi> grow <hi>fainter,</hi> then it will regain its force; undermine, and at laſt ruine, the <hi>Knowledge</hi> that had been rais'd: It will again captivate the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> and, like a barbarous Conquerour, put out its Eyes.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of our <hi>Duty</hi> impairs its <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> It is as a <hi>Sleep</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> and under its Truce our <hi>Carnal Deſires</hi> refreſh and gather ſtrength: there
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42782:13"/>is too a ceſſation of Senſe, as well as of Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; a preſent Forgetfulneſs of God, and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Ignorance of his Will. But if we are thence ingag'd into Actual Tranſgreſſion, we then avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly contradict his Precepts, and make open War againſt his <hi>Sacred Truths;</hi> deſtroying, as far as we can, all the Records of them, and breaking not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Commandments,</hi> but the <hi>Tables</hi> themſelves. The Knowledge of them is troubleſome and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and muſt be ſuppreſs'd.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Doing</hi> of any <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> a Blot is contracted; which not only blemiſhes the Soul, but blackens and darkens it: And a contrary Courſe of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance afterwards, is not more neceſſary to atone for the Guilt, than it is to change the Depravation of the Mind, and to recover and re-eſtabliſh its former Sentiments. For as there are ſome Vices, which naturally affect the Head, rendring it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to think and recollect, and diſabling it for any Science: ſo have All of them ſomething of that ſtupifying Nature, particularly indiſpoſing for <hi>Divine Knowledge;</hi> ſending up ſuch Fumes, as by a peculiar Malignancy aſſault and poiſon all No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> and mortifie the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Knowledge</hi> of our <hi>Duty,</hi> is as a <hi>Light</hi> ſet up within us, to be maintain'd by conſtant Supplies,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42782:14"/>and in perpetual Motion. It may be obſcur'd by the ſhining in of the World, through our Senſes and Imagination: it may be ſuffocated, if only by the Damp, ariſing from an earthy and yet not well purg'd Breaſt; grow pale and dim, and then go out: but by the active Contrariety of wicked and ungodly Practices, it is certainly extinguiſh'd, drown'd as by many Waters.</p>
            <p>So neceſſary is the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of our <hi>Knowledge,</hi> to its <hi>Preſervation.</hi> But then further,</p>
            <p n="3">3. By <hi>Doing of the Will of God,</hi> at length we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Habit of <hi>Doing it willingly;</hi> and begin to have new Pleaſure in the Diſcharge of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. According as our <hi>Carnal Affections</hi> are ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, our <hi>Spiritual Deſires</hi> ariſe; and upon the <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> of the <hi>Old Man,</hi> the <hi>New Man grows up,</hi> and <hi>improves:</hi> the Conſent of the <hi>Sanctified Will,</hi> being at laſt utterly and abſolutely given to the Aſſent of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> and we not only allowing the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to be true and reaſonable in the ſpeculation, but imbracing it with our whole heart, and intirely affectionate to it: proceeding ſo to the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of one <hi>farther Truth,</hi> deliver'd us by our Saviour, and experimentally diſcovering, that <hi>His Yoke is eaſie, and Burthen light;</hi> that <hi>His Paths are Paths of Pleaſure and Peace.</hi> This is the <hi>Seraphick State</hi> of <hi>Holy Men,</hi> who now believe not only what they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42782:14"/>have heard, but perceive and know what their <hi>Eyes have ſeen,</hi> and <hi>their Hands have handled,</hi> and their Souls have enjoyed, of the <hi>Word of Life.</hi> Then from the Heart, continuing its firſt Motion, and actuated with <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Zeal,</hi> freſh ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Spirits are ſent back again to the Head; the Warmth of the Breaſt is inkindled into a Flame; and <hi>New Light</hi> ſpringing up from that <hi>Holy Heat,</hi> the upper Sphaere of Man, like Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is full of <hi>Brightneſs</hi> and <hi>Joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this manner, the <hi>Knowledge of God's Will</hi> is to be improv'd by us; <hi>It comes by Hearing,</hi> and may be imagined by <hi>Meditation;</hi> but it really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes, ſtrengthens, and is fix'd, by <hi>Actions</hi> of <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> and reducing it into <hi>Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not therefore to be wonder'd, That ſuch as doe not <hi>thoſe things which are convenient,</hi> become of <hi>Reprobate Minds:</hi> and that they loſe the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, who like not to retain it.</hi> Neither ſhall we admire, if there are thoſe who are in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <hi>always learning, but never come to the Knowledge of Chriſt.</hi> Their Ears itch, and they heap up to themſelves <hi>Teachers;</hi> but their Hands are idle, their Feet are ſtraying, and their Souls have no Inclination to try, and to obey. They have heard much, and ſome Fancy of their Duty they may have, or may ſpeak its Language; they have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42782:15"/>wrote it may be, and can repeat: but the Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of all <hi>moral Diſcourſes</hi> ſhould be by <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> and they tranſcribed into our <hi>Converſation.</hi> They edifie not, they ſay, by this Man's Sermon: and by the <hi>Knowledge,</hi> from which they think they are edified, they may not be built, but <hi>puffed up.</hi> But how ſhould they edifie, who ſit ſtill only and hear? Faith being no more to be built up and finiſh'd by Preaching, than a Houſe would be ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Diſcourſe of the beſt Architect. Much leſs ſhould we expect a Superſtructure, if, as in the Confuſion of a <hi>Babel,</hi> their <hi>Actions</hi> agreed not with the <hi>Speech;</hi> and what was endeavoured to be raiſed at the <hi>Ear,</hi> they, with the <hi>fooliſh Woman,</hi> were ſtill <hi>pulling down with their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is to be the <hi>Conſolation</hi> of the <hi>illiterate,</hi> if honeſt-hearted, <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> that although there be thoſe that appear more knowing, are skill'd in the <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>God's Will,</hi> can give an account of all the <hi>Diſputes</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and can determine them; yet that all this is but ſmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and learned <hi>Ignorance,</hi> without any true <hi>Senſe,</hi> and ſound <hi>Judgment;</hi> that thoſe only are in the right <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>Divine Knowledge,</hi> who are <hi>obeying God,</hi> and <hi>obſerving his Will;</hi> they are the <hi>Profound</hi> and the <hi>Illuminate;</hi> and <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> as it <hi>ought to be known:</hi> their <hi>Light</hi> now <hi>ſhines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42782:15"/>men;</hi> and they ſhall <hi>ſhine as Stars</hi> for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>And may I further obſerve, that the <hi>Reflection</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> which gives an account of that <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> which oppoſes his <hi>Doctrine,</hi> gives too a reaſon of all the <hi>Differences</hi> and <hi>Debates</hi> that have been rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in it. For theſe would infallibly be much leſs, if not quite ceaſe, were thoſe, who <hi>eagerly diſpute his Will,</hi> as <hi>zealous</hi> and <hi>earnest</hi> to <hi>perform it:</hi> were not Men more warmly concerned for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Interest</hi> of their <hi>Party,</hi> or <hi>themſelves;</hi> than they are <hi>really deſirous</hi> to underſtand the <hi>Mind</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For if any one truly gives himſelf up to <hi>do his Will;</hi> he will not be apt to enter into needleſs <hi>Conteſts,</hi> about what is not <hi>practical;</hi> nor ſtrive moſt to <hi>know,</hi> what is not to be <hi>done:</hi> And then when he comes to the Queſtion, ſo much of his <hi>Lord's Will</hi> he will at firſt obſerve, as to be <hi>modeſt,</hi> and <hi>meek,</hi> and <hi>tractable;</hi> not ſuffer his <hi>Paſſions</hi> and <hi>Animoſities</hi> to join in the <hi>Enquiry:</hi> he will not bring ſo much as a Wiſh on one part, much leſs ſhall any <hi>humane Pre-ingagements</hi> decide the <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</hi> And if ſo, one cannot but think, (and ſure we are not in this <hi>partial</hi> our ſelves) that the <hi>Papal Infallibility,</hi> for Example, and their <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> would be no longer defended, nor their <hi>groſs Falſhoods</hi> be ſet up for <hi>Catholick Truths:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42782:16"/>on the other ſide, would ancient <hi>Laudable Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices</hi> be any longer <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi> Were we not <hi>carnal,</hi> and <hi>walked</hi> we not <hi>as Men,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring our ſelves, and doing our own Will; there might be neither <hi>Hereſie</hi> nor <hi>Schiſm;</hi> did we reſign our ſelves up to the <hi>Truth,</hi> on which ſide ſoever it ſhould appear. And certainly the <hi>Sacredneſs</hi> and <hi>Moment</hi> of the Cauſe, where <hi>God's Will</hi> is in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would require ſuch a Caution, as, in leſſer Matters, is inforc'd by an <hi>Oath;</hi> that we ſhould judge without <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Affection, Hatred</hi> and <hi>Malice;</hi> that thoſe at leaſt who take upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to judge of his <hi>Law,</hi> ſhould <hi>judge righteous Judgment.</hi> For what is fit to be ſaid after any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident that befals us by the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is as proper to be premis'd before a <hi>Diſpute</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Revelation: Thy will be done, O Father, which art in Heaven.</hi> And were our part of it <hi>done on Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> it might almoſt be known in the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>Happy it would be for the <hi>Arts,</hi> ſaid an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,</hi> if none but the <hi>Skilful</hi> and the <hi>Artiſts</hi> judg'd of them: and no leſs happy would it be for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> if only the <hi>truly religious,</hi> and the <hi>ſincere Chriſtian,</hi> were to determine the <hi>Points</hi> in <hi>Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> This Advantage would undoubtedly reſult,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42782:16"/>that the <hi>Diſputers</hi> would not be very <hi>many;</hi> as well as that the <hi>Diſputes</hi> would be no <hi>more</hi> than neceſſary; fairly debated, and ſoon compoſed. Whereas now all <hi>Religious Controverſies</hi> are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged like <hi>Wars</hi> for <hi>Religion;</hi> rais'd, and fought not always by the moſt <hi>Religious Men.</hi> The Queſtion is concerning ſome <hi>Point</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Manners;</hi> and ſhould be argued by <hi>Godly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:</hi> But the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> they come in and intermeddle; and they are as <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> on either ſide, whoſe Intereſt it is the <hi>Cauſe</hi> ſhould never be <hi>decided.</hi> For were not <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> divided, what <hi>Enemy</hi> would it have but thoſe its ſworn <hi>Enemies,</hi> againſt whom it had declar'd in <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> And againſt theſe it would then join its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Force</hi> in a <hi>Holy League,</hi> and never ceaſe until they were intirely ſubdued.</p>
            <p>In theſe many <hi>Differences</hi> of thinking, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Perſon, and Pleaſure, we piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope, that he will mercifully conſider the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and Errors of Men, and accept the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the Well-meaning; pardoning their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and want of Diſcernment, if not too careleſs and too wilful. But leſt we betray our ſelves and others into a further Miſtake, we ſhall do well to take along with us this his <hi>Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:42782:17"/>and remember that generally all our Ignorance is wilful, for want of Will to <hi>do God's Will.</hi> And when Ignorance ſhall come to be pleaded, <hi>in the day when He ſhall judge the ſecrets of mens hearts,</hi> it may then amount to no better an Excuſe, than if inſtead of ſaying, we did not Know his Will; we ſhould alledge in our <hi>Juſtification,</hi> that we were not willing to Doe it. Through our <hi>humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity,</hi> we did miſtake in the <hi>Duties</hi> of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</hi> but our Infirmity was this, That we were unwilling to obey. A much more abſurd return, than the <hi>careleſs Servant</hi> made in the <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> of the <hi>Talents:</hi> Lord, I knew that thou wert a hard Maſter, and didſt expect Obedience at my hands; and therefore I would not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thee.</p>
            <p>But it is not our Duty only, to inquire the <hi>Will of God;</hi> it is our Priviledge and Honour, to be able to underſtand it. Its Study is the nobleſt Exerciſe, and its Attainment the higheſt Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Rational Mind: the Knowledge ſo great a Favour, that we ſhould have endeavoured after it at any price; Should have bought that Learning with the expence of our Liberty; And to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Underſtand, ſhould have offered to Obey. That way the generous Appetite of Science,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42782:17"/>ſhould have mov'd in an Intelligent Creature; nor has God, in his ordinary method, vouchſafed to reveal himſelf to Man, on any other Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. His Diſciples are to be his vow'd Servants: to ſuch only will he appear, and certainly with no other will he dwell. Ever ſince the firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Attempt to Know his Will, by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing it; a Readineſs to obey, has been made the Preparative to that Knowledge; and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the Preſervative: the very <hi>Nature</hi> of his <hi>Doctrine</hi> requiring in us ſome Praediſpoſition, a probationary Obſequiouſneſs, without which it will not be imparted; and God having done it that Honour, as that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy</hi> ſhould of themſelves be render'd <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nqualified</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncapable,</hi> juſtly praecondemn'd to this Darkneſs now, <hi>to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever. For to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly,</hi> ſays God, <hi>What hast thou to do with my Law, ſeeing thou hatest to be reformed, and haſt caſt my Words behind thee?</hi> Be thou ignorant as thou art, as thou pretendeſt, or deſerveſt to be; and await the Iſſue. For a Deſire to Know, while we care not to Doe, is ſuch an impertinent, ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Curioſity, as can never be gratified by our Lord: and not to Doe, what we already Know,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42782:18"/>is ſo highly affronting, that there remains no bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Preſumption, but to pretend to further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; nor can a leſſer Puniſhment, for the Abuſe of this Knowledge, be expected, than its Forfeiture.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of God, however it may be eſteemed by Men, is valued by the Author; a <hi>Talent,</hi> committed to the Hopeful only, and the Promiſing; nor to any, but upon Account. If we put it to no Uſe, it will, of its own Nature, ruſt and diminiſh; may be loſt through Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or ſtoln by our Enemy, or taken away by the Great Owner. But, if we exerciſe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it, it will encreaſe and multiply, of it ſelf and by the natural Effect of our Induſtry; and will beſides be wonderfully bleſs'd and augmented by the Special Favour of our Lord: who is gone indeed into <hi>a far Country,</hi> but ſo, as ſtill to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, aſſiſt, and direct, the honeſt Care and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Labour of his Servants below.</p>
            <p>For, to our aſſured Encouragement, the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Power, that firſt openly introduced the Chriſtian Doctrine, ſtill inviſibly attends it; to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42782:18"/>cheriſh, as heretofore, the willing Beginning of its Diſciples, and to help on their obedient En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours. And this <hi>Will,</hi> whoever <hi>will Doe,</hi> not only <hi>will Know</hi> it in orderly Conſequence; but he <hi>ſhall Know</hi> it, ſupernaturally enabled by <hi>Divine Grace:</hi> our Performance as certainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded here, with a progreſſive Knowledge; as it ſhall be hereafter, with the Joys of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and his Immediate Beatifick Viſion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
